Guide to the Ralph Carlton Jenkins Papers MS 034
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Ralph Carlton Jenkins Papers
1933-1937
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Jenkins, Ralph Carlton, 1891-
MS 034
1 Linear Feet, 1 box
In 1935 Ralph Jenkins became Principal of the Danbury Normal School, and, in 1937 became the first President of Danbury State Teacher's College. Through his doctoral research he became an outstanding authority on the life and works of Henry Barnard. This is a collection of his papers and some titles from his collection of books.
Provenance
Transferred to the Archives in 1978.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Ralph C. Jenkins was born on December 3, 1891, in Springfield, Vermont. He earned his BA from Dartmouth College, MAs from Middlebury College and Harvard Graduate School of Education, and Doctorate from New York University. Through his doctoral research he became an outstanding authority on the life and works of Henry Barnard. Jenkins's writings include A Practical Program for Teacher Training in Vermont, Henry Barnard, Progressive Educator of Teachers, and, with Gertrude Warner, Henry Barnard-An Introduction.
After serving as principal of several high schools in Vermont, Jenkins came to Connecticut and was Superintendent of Schools in Putnam for three years and Plymouth for five years. He returned to Vermont as principal of the Johnson Normal School. In 1935 he became Principal of the Danbury Normal School, and, in 1937 became the first President of Danbury State Teacher's College.
As President of Danbury State Teacher's College, Jenkins worked with faculty to enlarge the curriculum, expand the library, and to promote the physical growth of the campus. One of Jenkins's priorities was to encourage men to enroll and enjoy the advantages Danbury Normal School had to offer in terms of a teaching career. Also, students were encouraged to stay in school and earn a "special" third year diploma that would enhance their training and thus become more desirable candidates for teaching positions. Soon thereafter students and faculty alike realized that a BA in education from the Danbury State Teacher's College was also needed.
Jenkins's interests were varied. He was active in many educational and civic organizations. In Danbury he was a Trustee of the library, a director of the Community Chest, and a prominent Rotarian, serving as District Governor of Rotary International in 1942. He also had a passion for music and sang in numerous church choirs. His love for music invariably carried over into the college where he felt the development of music ability and appreciation was important. He also had a keen interest in science and agriculture and was fascinated with the development of species and cultivation of a wide variety of vegetables and flowers.
Dr. Jenkins died on October 3, 1946.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Ralph C. Jenkins comprise one linear foot of materials and are arranged in two series: (1) Research Sources and Manuscript and (2) Books and Journals. The collection contains biographical and source materials on Henry Barnard, educator, editor, author, and lecturer collected from Ralph C. Jenkins who was President of Danbury State Teacher's College between 1935-1946.
The materials were collected in preparation for Jenkins's doctorial thesis Henry Barnard Progressive Educator of Teacher. The bulk of the collection consists of handwritten and typed excerpts of letters from the Monroe Collection at Couching Lion Farm, Waterbury, Vermont, that were sent to Barnard from educators across the country and Europe. Generally, the correspondents praise Barnard's works in educational reform and in some cases seek guidance to establish Normal Schools in their own states. Also included are excerpts from additional source materials, an array of pamphlets that contain Barnard's speeches as well as Connecticut School Documents praising him on his work in education reform that shaped the professional training of teachers.
Series 1 contains research sources and several drafts of Jenkins's manuscript.
Folders 10-15 contain Jenkins's first, second, and final draft of Henry Barnard--Progressive Educator of Teachers. The first and second drafts are comprised of typed excerpts from sources and arranged in a cut and paste format. Handwritten additions, marginal notes, and corrections along with preliminary chapter titles indicate these two drafts were a work in progress. Jenkins's final draft contains additional corrections and additions as well.
Series 2: Books and Journals. See container list for titles of journals and books contained in this collection.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 2 series:
Missing Title
Research Sources and Manuscript
Books and Journals.
Notes; Photographs.; Correspondence.; Clippings.; Education -- Periodicals.; Danbury (Conn.); Education -- History .; Books; Universities and colleges -- Administration.; Danbury Normal School -- History.; Barnard, Henry, 1811-1900.; American Journal of Education (Hartford, Conn.); Danbury State Normal School.; Connecticut Quarterly.; Jenkins, Ralph Carlton, 1891-; Maryland Historical Magazine.; New England Magazine.
- Series 1. Research Sources and Manuscript
  - Correspondence, 1838-1897 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    General note
    Folder 1 contains an alphabetical list of letters received by Barnard that are located in the Will S. Monroe Collection. Also included are excerpts of letters sent to Barnard from Thomas H. Palmer, L. P. Thompson, R. H. Quick, E. G. Gray, Jonathan Lamb, William S. Baker, and Samuel Lucas.
    Folder 2 contains several original letters to Barnard by Thomas H. Palmer during 1841-1842 as well as a transcript entitled "Barnard Letter Describing the Program at New Britain, Watkinson Collection, State Normal Schools."
  - Sources, 1850, 1881, 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Folder 3 contains two small booklets with notations regarding the Monroe letters and the Watkinson Collection, and a reprint from The Education Forum, November 1939 entitled "Henry Barnard-Educator of Teachers" by RCJ; the Twenty Seventh Annual Program for Patriotic Exercises in Schools dated May 3, 1935, in commemorating Rhode Island's Independence Day, May 4, 1776; "Educational Lore" reprinted from the Boston Sunday Herald, June 12, 1881; and, Connecticut Teachers' Institutes for 1850 by Henry Barnard.
  - Sources, 1860-1902 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Folder 4 contains Department of the Interior Bulletin, 1919, No.8, Life of Henry Barnard, The First United States Commissioner of Education, 1867-1870 by Bernard C. Steiner; and, miscellaneous pages from pamphlets concerning the teachers' institutes.
  - Sources, 1858-1891 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Folder 5 contains information from journals and letters regarding Kindergarten in Normal training, and on the Lyceum Movement, initially formed as local study groups, based on the belief that education should continue all through life regardless of age and gender. This movement also promoted the establishment of libraries, museums, and public schools.
  - Sources, 1897, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Folder 6 contains additional biographical information from The American Journal of Education on the occasion of Barnard's retirement. Included is a published letter to Governor Harrison of Connecticut by Barnard entitled "Connecticut Schools and Educators" dated February 3, 1886, and, an essay by Will S. Monroe entitled Henry Barnard: Sixty Years of Educational Activity. n.d.
  - New York University, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Folder 7 contains instructions from New York University in the preparation of theses or research reports as well as a rough draft of RCJ's intention to write his dissertation on Barnard from the "standpoint of today," i.e., 1937, rather than during Barnard's time.
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Folder 8 contains two photographs of Barnard, one as a young man, and the other as an elderly gentleman (circa 1900).
  - Bibliographic notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Folder 9 contains handwritten bibliographic notes.
  - Draft: Henry Barnard Progressive Educator of Teachers. A Synthesis of theContributions of Henry Barnard to the Education of American Teachers., 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Draft: Henry Barnard-Progressive Educator of Teachers, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - Final draft: Henry Barnard-Progressive Educator of Teachers, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
- Series 2. Books and Journals
  - Barnard, Henry, ed. American Journal of Education, 2nd Edition, Vol. I, Nos. 1 and 2. Hartford: Brownell, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Barnard, Henry, ed. American Journal of Education, Vol. I, Nos. 4, 6. Hartford: Brownell, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - Peters, Absalom, and Henry Barnard. The American Journal of Education and College Review. 1:2., 1856 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Barnard, Henry, ed. American Journal of Education, Vol. I, No. 7. Hartford: Brownell, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - New England Magazine, 14:5., 1896 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Maryland Historical Magazine, 8:3-4, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Barnard, Henry, ed. American Journal of Education for the Year 1829, Vol. IV. Boston: Carter and Hendee (Box 1, Folder *)
  - Norton, Frederick Calvin. "Henry Barnard, Educator," Connecticut Quarterly, April-June 1898, Vol. IV, 4:2, (1898): 122-137. (2c) (Box 1, Folder *)
  - Jenkins, Ralph C., and Warner, Gertrude Chandler. Henry Barnard, An Introduction. Hartford: The Connecticut State Teachers Association., 1937 (Box 1, Folder *)
    On Display